<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speedy advice to all Roman Catholicks; especially, those concerned in Scotland and Ireland</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O56aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153613</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153613)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2372:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Speedy advice to all Roman Catholicks; especially, those concerned in Scotland and Ireland</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin, near the Black-Bull, in the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Titus Oates.</note>
                  <note>Formerly identified as Wing S4909 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153613:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153613:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SPEEDY ADVICE TO ALL Roman Catholicks; Eſpecially, thoſe concerned in SCOTLAND AND IRELAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black-Bull,</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153613:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153613:2"/>
            <head>SOUND ADVICE TO <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THough there be none in this Nation, who (upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Merit) oweth leſs kindneſs to your Tribe, yet (as one well acquainted with the Intrigues of both Churches) upon the account of Brotherly Love and Charity, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſent you with my Chriſtian and beſt Advice, earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring you, ſeriouſly to conſider the ſandy Foundation of your Romiſh Church, and no more pin your Faith and confidence of Salvation, to the implicit aſſertions of a pretended Authority, and uſurped Supremacy; to believe every Contradiction of Nonſenſe, which is, or can be affirmed by the Spiritual Apoſtates, of ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable an <hi>Harlot,</hi> whom (with the <hi>Epheſians, Act.</hi> 19.28.) you term your <hi>Great Diana,</hi> and unſpotted <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> and therefore ought to be believed without any further enquiry; though the <hi>Turks</hi> may, on as good grounds, perſwade the World to embrace their Religion, and their chief <hi>Mufti</hi> as well claim Chriſt's Vicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, upon the account of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> can on the Succeſſion of <hi>Peter;</hi> their Principles being neither more ridiculous, nor contrary to the Scriptures of Truth, and Apoſtolick Chriſtian Faith, than the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is at this preſent time.</p>
            <p>Indeed, I my ſelf was lulled aſleep, by the allurements of the Popiſh <hi>Syrenes,</hi> and the bewitching Sorceries of the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> (as by the impetuous current of <hi>Babel</hi>'s ſtreams) driven headlong to the brink and ſhore of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Abominations: But as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſold to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for the Preſervation of his Brethren, ſo was I laid aſide, by the permiſſion of Divine Providence, for the ſafety both of my King and Country. Therefore (with the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153613:3"/>
Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was once a Perſecuter) <hi>knowing the terrour of the Lord,</hi> and the danger of Popiſh Apoſtacy, I perſwade all men to renounce <hi>the Doctrine of Devils,</hi> and embrace the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> freely offered to us in the Goſpel. And becauſe I would gain ground on the meaneſt Capacities, and diſcover the nakedneſs of the <hi>Roman Harlot, in puris,</hi> or (rather) <hi>nudis naturalibus,</hi> I ſhall (for the benefit of thoſe who have not money to buy, nor time to read, great Controverſies) ſet down in this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> ſome obvious and abominable Errours of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, in ſuch capital and legible Characters, that they who run may read MYSTERY BABYLON, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the face of that impudent Harlot; and (unleſs they ſhut their Eyes, Ears, and all their Senſes, the Gates of their underſtanding) be ready to cry out, <hi>Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt blow that I intend to ſtrike, is at the Pope's <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Infallibility,</hi> the two great Pillars whereon the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> (or rather <hi>Fabrick of Antichriſt</hi>) leaneth. The firſt, God hath as evidently prohibited, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.42. as he hath Murder and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in the ſixth and ſeventh Commandments; and ſince Papiſts unanimouſly acknowledge that all the Apoſtles received <hi>the gift of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> only the <hi>Keys,</hi> the <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Badge</hi> of his Supremacy, before they prove his Superiority and Dignity above the reſt of the Apoſtles, they muſt prove that thoſe Keys were a thing better and more precious than the reſt received; yea, than the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or <hi>God himſelf,</hi> which none but <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his Members dare to affirm. <hi>Peter,</hi> indeed, being a forward Man, Self-confident and Audacious, firſt anſwered our Saviour's Queſtion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.16. and our Saviour (very gently) continued his diſcourſe to him, not excluding the reſt: But were I to give the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy to any Apoſtle, I would rather give it to <hi>James</hi> the Lords Brother, or to <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Barnabas,</hi> to whom <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf gave <hi>the right hand of fellowſhip, Gal.</hi> 2.9. or to <hi>John,</hi> who could be more intimate with Jeſus than any of the reſt, as is clear from <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.23. and was termed <hi>the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved, Joh.</hi> 21.20. Yet what Fool will from thence conclude, that he hated all the reſt? though the <hi>Papists</hi> fooliſhly affirm, that becauſe Chriſt gave the <hi>Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> he gave them to none elſe: He was pleaſed to wheedle over the reſt with ſmaller enduements, priviledges, and preheminence; though they received both the <hi>Father and the Son.</hi> Thus did <hi>Peter</hi> (according to the Canon of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153613:3"/>
               <hi>Church of Rome</hi>) receive a more noble Gift, and was inſpired with a greater Spirit than God himſelf; though our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.29. <hi>My Father is greater than all.</hi> Yet, for all theſe Keys were ſo precious, that bloody <hi>Sodomite,</hi> Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Second, threw them in the River <hi>Tiber,</hi> as he was marching before his Army, the <hi>number whereof was as the ſand of the Sea:</hi> Whence <hi>Bibliander</hi> doth conclude, that Pope <hi>Julius</hi> did reſign all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Right and Power, <hi>of ſhutting and opening Heaven and Hell,</hi> to the River <hi>Tiber,</hi> or the Fiſhes or other Creatures therein. For caſting away the Keys, the Teſtimony of his Authority, he did deprive and ſpoil himſelf, and all his Succeſſors, of <hi>Peter</hi>'s inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
            <p>But (to approach a little nearer to this glorious <hi>Mitre,</hi> whoſe dazling brightneſs darkneth all the Crowns in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>) I would gladly know how the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> came to be <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, and if he came honeſtly by his Popedom: If <hi>Peter</hi> was Crucify'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> his Succeſſion muſt be by Uſurpation, and his Right to the Holy Chair, but a meer Robbery. But it is acknowledged by all, that the Titles of <hi>Pope of Rome, Univerſal Biſhop, Peter's Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, Chriſts Vicar, and God upon Earth,</hi> were not known till (about 600 years after our Saviour.) The Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> did both by Letters and Legates ſollicit the Emperour <hi>Mauritius</hi> for the Title of <hi>Biſhop of Biſhops,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Servus Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum.</hi> But <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt (abhorring that Blaſphemous Name, and calling it the Mark and Badge of Anti chriſt) <hi>Lib</hi> 4 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 27. wrote to the Emperour thus: <hi>Exclamare compellor, ac dicere, O tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora, O mores! Ecce cuncta in Europae Partibus Barbarorum juri ſunt tradita. Deſtructae Urbes, everſa Caſtra, depopulatae provinciae, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus terram Cultor inhabitat, &amp; tamen Sacerdotes qui in pavimento, &amp; cinere flentes jacere debuerunt, vanitatis ſibi nomina experiunt, &amp; novis ac prophanis vocabulis gloriantur.</hi> That is to ſay, I am compelled to cry out, O Times! O Manners! Behold in all the parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> all things live under the reverence of barbarous people: Towns are deſtroy'd, Caſtles are over-thrown, Provinces are ſpoiled: No Labourer inhabiteth the Land; notwithſtanding, the Prieſts (who ſhould lye in aſhes, upon the ground weeping) are ſeeking unto themſelves Names of Vanity, and Glory in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Titles. Thus <hi>Anti-chriſt's Title</hi> was blaſted in the bud, and forc'd to linger in the birth, till <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the Third (finding opportunity by the diſliking which the Emperour <hi>Phocas</hi> had of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153613:4"/>
the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) inſinuated himſelf in the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's ſavour, and obtained at his hands, that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> ſhould be called the <hi>Supream Head of all other Churches,</hi> and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Supream and Univerſal <hi>Biſhop of all Biſhops.</hi> Then <hi>Boniface.</hi> (as <hi>Platina</hi> writeth) proud of his Vain, Glorious, New Title (which he had ſnatch'd from the hand of an Uſurper) called a Council at <hi>Rome,</hi> conſiſting of ſeventy two <hi>Biſhops,</hi> thirty <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> and three <hi>Deacons;</hi> wherein, the priviledge of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> given by <hi>Phocas</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, was publiſhed. Thus he who had murdered an Emperour could make a Biſhop, and add luſtre to his ambitious <hi>Holineſs;</hi> and againſt the Nature both of Reaſon and Philoſophy, give that which in himſelf he had not.</p>
            <p>Thus was this proud ſwelling Title Midwif'd to the World, by a Tyrant who had Murdered his Maſter, the good Emperour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> with his Brother, Wife and Children. And as <hi>Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> obſerveth, the <hi>Eagles three Heads,</hi> with their bloody Bills, awaked all at once, <hi>viz. Boniface, Phocas,</hi> and <hi>Mahumet</hi> the <hi>Arabian.</hi> Now conſidering theſe things, and that the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> oweth his Greatneſs and Supremacy to the Emperour, what Maſter of Ingratitude is he, to Curſe, Excommunicate, Depoſe, and tread him under his Feet? Cauſe him to hold his Stirrup, Crown him with his Feet, force him to ſtand bare-foot, begging at his Gates, Poiſon him, and make him lye rotting above ground, without a Grave to lye in.</p>
            <p>Neither can the Pope deduce his <hi>Infallibility</hi> from <hi>Peter</hi>'s conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſtedfaſtneſs of <hi>Faith;</hi> for he (after he had received the Keys) both could, and did fall, and was by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23. not called <hi>His Holineſs,</hi> but <hi>Satan:</hi> whence I might (after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Popiſh Argumentation) infer that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is built upon <hi>Satan,</hi> who denyed his Saviour, and was ignorant, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13, 14, whether it was lawful to eat with the Gentiles, till <hi>Paul</hi> informed and confirmed him in the true Faith. Yea, all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts fooliſhly conclude and affirm, that, during the time of Chriſt's Crucifixion, none upon Earth, no not the Apoſtles themſelves, had true Faith, or believed in the Son of God, but only the B. Virgin: whence it will follow (according to the Principles of Popery) that the Church was built upon an Unbeliever, and that the <hi>Devils,</hi> the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> did prevail againſt it.</p>
            <p>Now then, if <hi>Peter</hi> was neither <hi>Supream</hi> nor <hi>Infallible,</hi> why doth the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> father his Fopperies of Supremacy and infallibility
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153613:4"/>
on him? as by a Goſpel Line, and Spiritual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, could prove his Right to the Holy Chair, and throw down all his Brats of Abomination, at the Bleſſed Apoſtle's Door. But if I can, by demonſtration, prove the <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> his pretended <hi>Holineſs,</hi> an <hi>Infidel</hi> in Faith, and an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> in Life and Converſation, I hope all ingenious Papiſts will acknowledge him <hi>Fallible;</hi> for, <hi>ab actu ad potentiam bene valet conſequentia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt proof I ſhall bring is a ſhort Hiſtory, taken out of the beſt Popiſh Writers, which is this; <hi>Formoſus</hi> the firſt Reigned ſix Years, and died <hi>anno</hi> 896. after he had made many Decretals, Acts and Church-Canons, which <hi>Steven</hi> the 6th ſpitefully annulled and cancelled, as wicked and abominable, becauſe he had prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in the Popedom, and would not allow him Concubines to his mind: Yea (to revenge his undeſerved quarrel againſt him) ſummoning a Council, he cauſed his dead rotten Carcaſs to be digg'd out of the Grave, and deckt with Gorgeous Pontificals, and pulling off all again, to be array'd in Lay-mens habit. Thus the dead Body being degraded and deveſted of all Eccleſiaſtick Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like a ſuperſtitious Fool, he cut off the two Fingers of his right hand (wherewith he us'd to hold the Sacrament) and threw them in the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> and afterwards commanded his Body to be buried among <hi>Lay-men.</hi> But <hi>Romanus</hi> the firſt, ſucceeding <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> allowed and confirmed the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling and condemning the Canons, Acts and Decretals of <hi>Steven,</hi> as wicked and abominable. Then after the Death of <hi>Romanus,</hi> Pope <hi>John</hi> the tenth being a Favourite of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> made a General Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all the Writs and Proceſſes againſt the dead Body of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and condemned the Pope <hi>Steven</hi> his <hi>Council,</hi> and all their Writings. Till <hi>Sergius</hi> the third (who had before, by the Roman Clergy, been elected Pope with <hi>Formoſus,</hi> but ſuppreſſed by Faction) digg'd up the dead rotten Body of <hi>Formoſus</hi> the ſecond time; which had been in the Grave about ten Years, ſet it in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, drew it thence by the Heels to a block, and ſtrook off its head: And chopping off the three fingers, which <hi>Steven</hi> had leſt, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the rotten, ſtinking Maſſacred Body to be thrown into the River <hi>Tyber:</hi> And laſtly, defaced, anulled and condemned all his Acts and Decrees, which before had been allowed, denyed, confirmed and condemned by ſeveral thwarting and contradicting Popes. Till in the Reign of Pope <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> the third, about the year 913, ſome Fiſhermen found the Body of <hi>Formoſus</hi> in the River <hi>Tyber,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153613:5"/>
which was by his <hi>Holineſs</hi> buryed ſumptuouſly; the very Images (if you can believe the famous Popiſh Writers) welcoming, nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſaluting the dead Body when it was brought into the Church. Now of neceſſity ſome of theſe contradicting Popes were erroneous in their Judgments; yea, both faulty and Heretical, and did fall in their <hi>Faith,</hi> and ſacrifice their Conſcience to their ſpleen: For, contradicting one another, they could not all be in the right, nor affirm that whicn was true and Orthodox. For it is an undeniable maxim, that <hi>Duo contradictoria nequiunt eſſe ſimul ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> But, whatever was their <hi>Faith,</hi> I am ſure their <hi>Charity</hi> was thred-bare, and their <hi>Holineſſes</hi> deſtitute of all mercy, vindictive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purſuing their holy Father beyond the Gates of Death, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging their quarrel in the very Grave. Neither was this all, for it is obſerved by Popiſh Writers, and all others ſince, that after the Death of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> poiſon'd and diſpatch'd one another ſo faſt, that there were eleven Popes within nine years ſpace.</p>
            <p>The next proof of the Pope's Fallibility in <hi>Faith,</hi> is, that <hi>John</hi> the 23d was proved an <hi>Heretick</hi> in the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> by theſe words; <hi>Pope</hi> John <hi>ſaid, and ſtubbornly believed, that the Soul of Man dyeth together with the Body, and is conſumed to nothing, like the Souls of Bruit Beaſts.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Thomas Walleis,</hi> an Engliſh-man, was Impriſoned by the Pope for reproving his Hereſie, the King of <hi>France</hi> ſummoned a <hi>Council</hi> into his Palace, in <hi>Viciana Sylva,</hi> where the whole Aſſembly ſubſcribed againſt the Pope's Hereſie: And the King wrote to <hi>John</hi> to reform it, and ſet the Priſoner at liberty. The laſt he did to prevent threatning dangers; but of his Hereſie, he never would purge himſelf.</p>
            <p>My third proof ſhall be from Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. This man was an Adulterer, a great Sorcerer and Necromancer; and (as <hi>Beno</hi> the Cardinal writeth) when he was in his merry Fits, would caſt off his Sleeves, and skip and dance like a Bear, in form of ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles and flames of fire: With which, and many ſuch Miracles (or rather lying Wonders) he deceived and perſwaded ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to believe that he was <hi>a Lamp of pure Holineſs.</hi> As alſo, he kept a Brazen-Head in his Cloſet, wherein dwelt a Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with (in any danger) he conſulted, to know the reſult of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. But on a certain time (as he was preparing to War againſt the Emperour) his Domeſtick God gave him ſuch an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Anſwer, that he could make no ſenſe of it: therefore took
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153613:5"/>
               <hi>the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper</hi> (his ſuppoſed Deity) and ſetting it on a Table, Conjur'd it with the ſame Words that he had his <hi>Brazen-Head,</hi> a little before; but the <hi>Sacrament</hi> giving him no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>His Holineſs,</hi> in a great paſſion, threw it in the fire, with theſe Words, <hi>There's a God indeed: Could the Idol-Gods of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens give them Anſwer in their Succeſs, and canſt thou give me none?</hi> The Cardinals then preſent, were much diſpleaſed that <hi>Hildebrand</hi> ſhould have burn'd the God which they had made to be eaten: Therefore <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Portua</hi> (of the Popes Privy Council) made his Apology in a Sermon in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, the next Lord's Day, thus: <hi>What meaned HILDEBRAND and We to do theſe things, for which We all deſerve to be burned alive?</hi> From whence I infer, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> was an <hi>Heretick,</hi> and did not believe <hi>the real Preſence,</hi> and that the Sacrament was a <hi>True God.</hi> Yet this <hi>Gregory, alias Hildebrand,</hi> or <hi>Hell-brand</hi> (as ſome term him) for all he Poyſon'd ſeven Popes, to make way for himſelf to the Popedom, dyed at <hi>Salerne</hi> in great Miſery, <hi>Anno</hi> 1086.</p>
            <p>My fourth proof is by conſequence, from the Words of Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> concerning the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; who, againſt the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Biblioth. patr. Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Surely the Sacraments which we receive, of the Body and Blood of our Lord, are a Divine thing, ſo that by them we are made partakers of a Divine Nature, and yet it ceaſeth not to be the Subſtance or Nature of Bread and Wine, and certainly, the Image and Reſemblance of Chriſt's Body and Blood are Celebrated in the Action of the Myſtery.</hi> Whence it will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly follow, that he was a <hi>Heretick,</hi> according to the Canon of the ſecond Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which confirmed the Doctrine of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> or elſe that all the Popes ſince have been Hereticks, who have maintained Chriſts real preſence, in the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My fifth and laſt proof ſhall be of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the X. who (when Cardinal <hi>Bembus</hi> moved a Queſtion out of the Goſpel) very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly Anſwered, <hi>All Ages can teſtify enough, how profitable that Fable of Chriſt hath been to us, and our Company.</hi> Who then dare be ſo impudent to affirm him Infallible in Faith, who denyeth the very foundation thereof, and him by whom only Salvation can be obtained? <hi>Be aſtoniſhed, O ye Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid, &amp;c. Jer.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>Now if this be the Fountain of the <hi>Romiſh Faith,</hi> and the Creed of <hi>his unſpotted Holineſs,</hi> what mud and dirt is in <hi>Babel</hi>'s <hi>ſtreams?</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153613:6"/>
What Atheiſm and Infidelity muſt there be among the Crew of. the Romiſh Clergy? And Rabble of Brutiſh Prieſts, Monks and Friers? <hi>Eſt petri Sedes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarm. in praefat. ante lib. de Pontif. Rom.) Lapis probatus, angularis, pretioſus, in fundamento fundatus.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Chair is an approved Corner Stone, precious, and laid in the foundation.</hi> And again (<hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de pont. Rom. cap.</hi> 31.) <hi>The Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>is the foundation of the Church.</hi> And <hi>Stapleton (Relect. princip. Doctr. in praef.) Alii nunc a Chriſto eorumve Doctrina, praedicatio, determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio fundamenti apud me locum habebunt.</hi> That is <hi>others (now beſide Chriſt) and their Doctrine, Preaching, and Determination, ſhall be eſteemed of me as a Foundation.</hi> The Begging Friers in the time of <hi>William de ſanct. amore</hi> (as the Doctors of <hi>Paris in lib. de peric. noviſ. temp.</hi> relate) collected all their Dreams, Fancies, and vain Traditions, into one Volume, calling it the <hi>Eternal Goſpel,</hi> and Preach'd <hi>The Goſpel of Chriſt ſhall ceaſe, and our Eternal Goſpel ſhall be Preach'd and receiv'd to the end of the World.</hi> The Pope with great reluctancy, did at laſt condemn this blaſphemous Book of Abominations, and lying Wonders, at the earneſt Requeſt of the Doctors of <hi>Paris,</hi> againſt whom <hi>his Holineſs</hi> conceived ſuch implacable hatred, that he could never after be reconciled to them, and favoured the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars ſo much, that he both preferr'd them, and enlarg'd their Priviledges.</p>
            <p>Now if any of the Romiſh Clergy perſwade a Lay-man to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as the Church believeth, he muſt tell him what is the Church. For if he believe what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> preach'd formerly, then he muſt not believe the Doctrine of Popery now. Yea, if he believe Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> (whom I have Quoted) he muſt not believe the preſent <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> or elſe if he will believe the Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> now, he muſt acknowledge that Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> was a curſed Heretick, which will overturn the Doctrine of the <hi>Popes Infallillility,</hi> which hangeth betwixt a <hi>Poſſibility</hi> and an <hi>Impoſſibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to prove the Pope Fallible, in reſpect of evil Works, Sin and Wickedneſs, his godleſs and brutiſh life is enough to declare him both a Beaſt and an Atheiſt. And I really believe, that as ſoon as ever he ſitteth down in the old rotten Stool, which they call St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Chair</hi> (as from an old enchanted Oracle) he is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the ſpirit of Deluſion and Errour; which driveth him headlong to all Abominations and Uncleanneſs. And, as an evil ſpirit from God, troubled <hi>Saul;</hi> ſo ſuffereth he <hi>the wicked one</hi> to take poſſeſſion of this <hi>Prince of Pride,</hi> that they who follow and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153613:6"/>
after him, and term him <hi>His Holineſs,</hi> may be inexcuſable in the day of their accounts; in reputing him a <hi>Terreſtial God,</hi> whom they ſee an <hi>Infernal Devil.</hi> And for further ſatisfaction, I ſhall here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert ſome Popiſh Pranks, and Wicked Villanies, committed by the Popes of <hi>Rome;</hi> which the Reader may judge, whether or not they can conſiſt with <hi>Infallibility</hi> and unſpotted <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pope</hi> (or rather <hi>Popeſs) Joan</hi> was a <hi>Fornicatrix,</hi> and died in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, bringing forth a Baſtard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pope John</hi> XIII. lay with his own Siſters, forced his Fathers Concubines, played at Dice, drank the Devils good Health, pray'd to him for good luck, and put out the Eyes of <hi>Benedict</hi> his Ghoſtly Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. cauſed a fellow to put great ſtones, right over the place where the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> uſed to pray, in St. <hi>Marys</hi> Church, to knock him on the Head, by an ingenious contrivance; whilſt he was at his Devotion, he Curſed, and Excommunicated him, without occaſion, and took his Crown from him, without any juſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſchal</hi> II. ſtirred up <hi>Henry</hi> the V. to Rebel againſt his good Old Father, who at laſt (by his aſſiſtance) beat him from the Empire, and brought him to beg his Bread; ſo that he lived and died mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and was cauſed to lye rotting above ground, without burying, five years, at the Pope's ſpecial command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> IV. called <hi>Henry</hi> III. King of <hi>England</hi> his Vaſſal, Slave and Page, whom he could impriſon, and put to open ſhame, at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hadrian</hi> IV. fell out with the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> for holding his wrong Stirrup.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> III. took from <hi>John,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> both his Crown and Kingdom, and gave it to <hi>Lewis,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Son, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any juſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Celeſtine</hi> III. Crowned the Emperour and Empreſs of <hi>Germany</hi> with his Feet, and (throwing off the Crowns again with his Toe) ſaid, <hi>I have power both to make and unmake Kings and Emperours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicolas</hi> III. begot a Baſtard Son, that had Claws and Hair like a Bear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. becauſe <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> would not ſuffer the Revenues of his Kingdom to be tranſported to Foreign Countries, Curſed both him and his, to the fourth Generation. He likewiſe gave Authority to Eccleſiaſtick Perſons in <hi>England,</hi> to deliver the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153613:7"/>
people to Satan twice a year. This man came by the Popedom after a moſt deviliſh and treacherous manner; for finding his Maſter, Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Fifth, a ſimple doting Man, he hired one of his Bed-chamber to make a Ghoſtly noiſe, in a long Reed, through a hole which he had cauſed to be made privately, in the Wall of his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s Chamber, crying, <hi>CELESTINE, CELESTINE, give over thy Charge, for it is above thy ſtrength and ability.</hi> The Old Man (thinking the Infernal noiſe had been the Voice of an Angel, ſent from Heaven) in ſpite of all oppoſers, gave over the Popedom on St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s <hi>Eve,</hi> and went to a Deſart to lead an Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit's life, (as <hi>Maſſaeus</hi> writeth.) But the Impoſtor <hi>Boniface</hi> (who had thus cheated the ſimple man, and gotten to be his Succeſſor, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the people would follow him as Pope) apprehended Old <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> and put him in cloſe Priſon, where he lay till the day of his Death: But <hi>Boniface</hi> himſelf, did not eſcape the juſt Judgment of God, for he dyed in a miſerable condition, with a guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This is he, of whom it was ſaid, <hi>He enter'd like a FOX, he reigned like a LYON, and dyed like a DOG.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> the V. cauſed his Hang-man to take <hi>Francis Dandalus,</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Duke, and bind him with Chains, and throw him at his Feet under his Table, where (for very hunger) he gnaw'd bones like a Dog.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> VI. cauſed to Poyſon the Emperour <hi>Lewis,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe but Pride, Covetouſneſs, and deſire of Superiority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Urban</hi> VI. drowned ſeven Cardinals, becauſe he ſuſpected that they had conſpired againſt him with <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> his Competitor, an <hi>Antipope.</hi> This <hi>Urban</hi> (whom ſome termed <hi>Turban,</hi> for his wicked and troubleſome life) as he was in haſte riding from <hi>Naples,</hi> with his Spiritual Court of Rogues, and <hi>Sodomites,</hi> cauſed one of his Cut-throats to kill the Biſhop of <hi>Aquilo</hi> his Priſoner, leaving his dead mangled body on the way; becauſe (after his racking and tormenting) he could not ride ſo faſt as <hi>His Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> IV. gave liberty to ſeveral Families of the Clergy, to defile their bodies with all manner of filthineſs and brutiſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, for the three hot months, <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> VIII. begat ſixteen Children, on ſixteen ſeveral Women, and was ſo brutiſh every way, that after his Death this <hi>Epitaph</hi> was made upon him:
<q>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153613:7"/>
                  <l>Octo Nocens pueros genuit, totidem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> puellas,</l>
                  <l>Hunc merito poterit dicere Roma patrem.</l>
                  <l>Spuricies, Gula, avaritia at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ignavia, Deſes,</l>
                  <l>Hoc, octave jacent, quo tegeris tumulo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benedict</hi> the XII. bought with a large ſumm of money, the Siſter of <hi>Francis Petrarch,</hi> a very beautiful Woman, to ſatisfie his Carnal deſire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the VI. lay with his own Daughter, on whom after her death this Epitaph was made:
<q>
                  <l>Hic jacet in tumulo, Lucretia nomine; ſed re</l>
                  <l>Thais; Alexandri filia, ſponſa, nuras.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> III. in diſguiſe, lay with a young Gentlewoman, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Wooing her, by whom he had a Son called <hi>Peter Aloyſius,</hi> the expreſs Image of ſuch a Father: For being General of his Father's Army, he cauſed his Souldiers violently to hold the Godly Old Biſhop of <hi>Fane,</hi> till he in ſpite of the poor Old Man's heart, committed that abomination with him, that is neither proper to be Written, nor ſpoken of; the Biſhop afterwards dying for very grief. This Pope <hi>Paul</hi> had a Daughter named <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> whoſe Husband he poiſon'd, to enjoy her perſon with greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, and with her, to wallow in uncleanneſs. With whom alſo, her Brother <hi>Peter Aloyſius,</hi> in imitation of his Father, made bold to commit Inceſt. This Pope alſo kept a Liſt of 45000 Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots about <hi>Rome,</hi> which paid him a monthly Tribute for Liberty of Whoring.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Demonſtrations of the Pope's Fallibility, and the fruits of his <hi>manifeſt Wickedneſs.</hi> Theſe are the doings of the <hi>Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> and the wicked Works of the Romiſh <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> which (to number up all, or as many of them as have been publiſhed in Popiſh Hiſtorians) would make a book larger than twenty Church Bibles: But <hi>ex ungue Leonem,</hi> We may know by this little what the whole Volume would be, and what metal the <hi>Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> is made of. Are theſe the Works of him that hath the Spirit of God, or the Spirit of Anti-chriſt? Tell me ingenuouſly Reader, how you reliſh this drop of the Cup of Romiſh Abominations, and if you can digeſt a whole Draught of it, without Poyſoning your Conſcience? Doth it ſurfeit your Soul to a future forbearance, and force you to cry out, O <hi>Man of God, Death is in the Cup?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that I object, againſt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> is the keeping the <hi>Laity</hi> from reading the Holy Scriptures. It is life
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153613:8"/>
eternal to know God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. but how to know the God of Truth without the knowledge of the Scriptures of Truth, I never could yet find out, they being the right way, and appointed guide, to lead us unto Chriſt himſelf. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures.</hi> And it was the commendation of the Noble <hi>Bereaus, Act.</hi> 17.11. that they tried the truth of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine, by the Touch-ſtone and Scriptures of Truth: <hi>For the Spirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> All the Apoſtles wrote to the Saints in general, and <hi>Paul</hi> deſired the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> to read his Epiſtle pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, in the Churches, and charged the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> by the Lord, to read his Epiſtle unto <hi>all the holy brethren.</hi> Now ſhall I conclude that there are no Saints but great ones, and learned Doctors: No Church or Congregation but what conſiſteth of Learned Rabbies and Clergy-men: No Brethren but Biſhops, Abbots, Prieſts, Monks and Friers, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> God forbid! For as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Conf. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Men unlearned earneſtly contend for Heaven, whilſt learned Men, without understanding, wallow in fleſh and blood.</hi> And although <hi>Paul</hi> wrote many things <hi>hard to be underſtood, which the unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable wrest,</hi> yet did not <hi>Peter</hi> (who giveth an <hi>Item</hi> of it, in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle, 3.16.) deſire his Writings to be taken from them. Meat and Drink muſt not be rejected, becauſe of Drunkards and Gluttons. Better ſome men be Debauch'd, than all the World Starv'd. Better there be a poſſibility of ſome's wreſting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than that all the World ſhould lye in Ignorance. Since He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies <hi>muſt be, that they who are approved may be made manifeſt,</hi> as good they be, by this means as other ways. Yet <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Scripturarum ignoratio haereſes peperit.</hi> And again, <hi>Barathrum est Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum ignoratio.</hi> Whence I may rationally infer, that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhutteth the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the Rabble of vulgar Papiſts (who dare not read nor know the Scriptures) in a broad way to Hell.</p>
            <p>Certainly it is the juſt condemnation of the World that men love to walk in Darkneſs, when they may walk in Light. And although the Scriptures be but a Riddle and Sealed Book to the Wicked, yet are the ſecrets of the Lord with thoſe that fear him. They are a <hi>Sun,</hi> which ſhow themſelves with their own Rays, if within our Horizon, giving light to the humble, dazling the curious eye, and ſtriking the ambitious ſpirits blind: A River, wherein an Elephant may ſwim, and an Infect wade and drink: A Feaſt, affording Milk for Babes; and ſtrong Meat for Men of underſtanding: They are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153613:8"/>
an inexhauſtible Treaſure, to which God hath promiſed his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and continual preſence, <hi>Iſah.</hi> 59.21. <hi>The everlaſting Goſpel</hi> is convey'd with an Angel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. This is that Light and Sun which the Man of Sin hath put under the Buſhel of prohibition; and (as it is Propheſied, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10.) made the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt full of darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is the earneſt deſire of my Soul, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> grant to all her Children the priviledge of reading the Holy Scriptures, and ſhew her ſelf the true Mother, by feeding, and not the Step-Mother, by ſtarving her Children; leſt her Flock go aſtray, and periſh in Ignorance, and their blood be required at the Clergy-men's hands: For <hi>if the Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3:</p>
            <p>My third Objection ſhall be againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Venial Sins;</hi> for though ſome ſins be more heinous in the ſight of God than others, yet is no ſin ſmall or venial. The <hi>Law of God</hi> is a fiery Law, every ſpark burneth. <hi>The wages of Sin</hi> (without exception) <hi>is Death.</hi> God's Wrath and Curſe hangeth over the head of every ſin, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. But ſince all conclude, that every ſin, by Nature, is evil, <hi>let us abſtain from all filthineſs both of the fleſh and of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My fourth Objection ſhall be againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> which Papiſts term <hi>a Place, or Pit of fire, Ordained by God, for purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Souls of Men after Death, from Venial Sins.</hi> But this Doctrine <hi>nititur facto ſuppoſito;</hi> for if there be no <hi>Venial Sins,</hi> then is there no Purgatory. But (in few words) there can be no unſanctify'd Saints, God doth not pardon by halfs; <hi>he forgiveth all thine Iniquities, he healeth all thy Diſeaſes, Pſal.</hi> 103.3. <hi>The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi> It were a ridiculous piece of Nonſenſe, for a King to pardon a Malefactor of his Murder, and yet cauſe him to be whipp'd at the Cart for his provoking Language. God doth not forgive great heinous Sins, and retain ſmall ones; <hi>he taketh away</hi> (as ſaith the Prophet) <hi>all our iniquities, healeth all our back-ſlidings,</hi> forgiveth us freely, loveth us freely, maketh us pure and clean, whiter than the Snow, and preſerveth us ſpotleſs, till we appear before him. They that continue in ſin, in expectation of a <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> may be miſtaken, and fall <hi>in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone; which is the ſecond Death, Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>My fifth Objection ſhall be againſt the Popiſh <hi>Limbus Infantum,</hi> an imaginary place, where the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy bar up all unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Infants, eternally, from the preſence of God. This is an
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153613:9"/>
uncharitable Opinion, and cannot conſiſt with the goodneſs, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, wiſdom, and fore-knowledge of God, who hath found out and ordained a ſufficient Remedy for loſt man, which under ſome circumſtances cannot be adminiſtred; for, <hi>fruſtranea eſt illa poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quae nequit reduci in actum.</hi> Now, I hope, the Papiſts will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſome Children are ſanctify'd in the Mothers Womb, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. and if ſuch a Child ſhould dye without Baptiſm, who dareth to affirm that he is ſeparated from the preſence of that God, who hath promiſed to be both the God of the faithful and of their ſeed?</p>
            <p>My ſixth Objection ſhall be againſt Popiſh Baptiſm: For, what a brutiſh thing is it to adulterate the Water and Element of this Holy Sacrament with Oyl, Salt and Spittle. Is ſenſual man wiſer than the Omnipotent God? <hi>If he Work, who can lett?</hi> And who can ſay unto the <hi>King of Kings, what doſt thou?</hi> Every thing ought to be done in decency and order, but this naſty and brutiſh trick is the ſhame of Sacraments, the bluſh of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the impudence of Popery, and the abſurdity of abominations. Will it not ſatisfie you <hi>to eat up the good Paſtures,</hi> but (with the Idol-ſhepherds in old) <hi>to tread down the reſidue with your feet.</hi> Will it not ſatisfie you to eat <hi>God's Body,</hi> Cancel the Scriptures, and debar the people from the Word of God, but muſt you alſo ſpit on his Sacrament, Homolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the deeds of <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and of thoſe Wicked <hi>Jews</hi> who ſerved him ſo when they Crucify'd him? Will it not ſatisfie you to drink all the Wine at his Supper, unleſs you ſpit in this Element of Water, becauſe it doth not anſwer your drunken Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites? O wretched Hypocrites! <hi>How can ye eſcape the Damnation of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what a ridiculous wicked thing is it to Baptize Bells, Churches, and other Eccleſiaſtical Neceſſaries, in the Name of Chriſt; Whether is it, to mock or ſpite the Chriſtian Religion? Did he ever Dye for Metal, Stones, and Wood? Were theſe the poſterity of <hi>Adam?</hi> Have Stocks and Stones, Wood and Metal, Immortal Souls? And has Chriſt commanded ſome Stones (ſuch as are in Church-Walls) and ſuch Metal as is moulded in Bells, and ſuch Wood as is converted to <hi>Roods,</hi> and wherewith we Roof Churches, to be Baptized, and not every Pot and Pan, Stick and Stone, we meet with? If they have right to the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> why not to the Word? And why do you not Preach to them? Why do you not Adminiſter to them the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> ſince he can eat and drink with the Prieſt's mouth as well as other <hi>Laicks?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſeventh Objection ſhall be againſt the Popiſh Euchariſt, wherein
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153613:9"/>
they pretend both to make and eat God, as is affirmed by <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencius,</hi> in his Myſteries of the Maſs, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Panis in Cristum tranſubſtantiatur &amp; ita in Creatorem; ſic ergo Creatura quotidie, fit Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi> And <hi>Bonner,</hi> in praiſe of the Prieſthood, ſaith, <hi>The Prieſts are Creators of their Maker.</hi> Truly it is moſt certain, that at the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of this Holy Sacrament, Chriſt in a Myſtery is more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly preſent, than at other times: But to ſay that Chriſt, at his laſt Supper, did eat up all and whole Chriſt; and that the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the eaten were the ſame; and that the Apoſtles were Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, and did eat Chriſt alive; when he was dead in his Grave; and that the B. Virgin did cruelly tear in pieces, and eat up her own Son, every bit and crum; and that God in Chriſt (who made Men Rational, and is the Author of Order and not Confuſion) did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the World both in Senſe and Reaſon; and that in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is <hi>Form</hi> without <hi>Subſtance,</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> without <hi>Form,</hi> and yet no <hi>Forma Subſtantialis;</hi> and that Chriſt's Body is in Heaven, Earth, <hi>France, Spain, Italy,</hi> and all the World over at once; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bilocation or Ubiquity: Or, (in few Words) to affirm that a Wicked Debauch'd Prieſt, can make that which was never unmade, <hi>viz.</hi> The Eternal ever-living holy God, and then eat up the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deity; is ſuch a piece of ridiculous, impudent, abſurd, brazen-fac'd, blaſphemous, ſelf-contradicting Nonſenſe, as driveth the Turks, Pagans, and Heathens, to aſtoniſhment; ſtaineth Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and confirmeth all ungodly Wretches in Atheiſm and Idolatry, and ought not to be named among Chriſtians. For as <hi>Vigil. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra. Eutych.</hi> (ſpeaking of Chriſts Body) ſaith, <hi>When it was on Earth, ſurely it was not in Heaven: And now becauſe it is in Heaven, certainly it is not on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My eighth Objection ſhall be againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her <hi>Laity</hi> of the <hi>Communion-Cup:</hi> For if our Saviour was ſo liberal of his Body and Blood, as to give both to unlearned Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yea to <hi>Judas,</hi> (whom he knew to be both a Thief and a Traytor) I think the Romiſh Clergy may do the ſame to the vulgar, after Confeſſion, without fear of the falling of drops of blood, or mammocks of fleſh; for it was no leſs diſparagement to Chriſt's Body and Blood, to be in the Self-murdering Son of Perdition's Belly, than to lye in a Church floor.</p>
            <p>My ninth Objection ſhall be againſt the Doctrine of Popiſh <hi>Merit;</hi> For if <hi>Man, in his best eſtate,</hi> be but <hi>Vanity,</hi> all his righteouſneſs and beſt performances but <hi>filthy rags,</hi> and the beſt of men but <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153613:10"/>
Servants:</hi> What can fooliſh men merit at the hand of God? Or what reward can he expect for his empty performances? Yet are the deluded Papiſts ſo ſimple, as to affirm that many of their <hi>ſuppoſed Saints</hi> did live ſo holily, that they left in bank a <hi>ſuperplus</hi> ſtock of good Works, more than merited Heaven to themſelves, and Wicked Kinſmen, which now <hi>his Holineſs of Rome</hi> hath laid up in bank as Spiritual Revenues, to be ſold to ungodly rich ſinners for ready Money, to buy their Salvation, and redeem their deceas'd Friends out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> But this principle is ſo evidently abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that there is no need to refute it to a Rational Man; for there can be no greater abſurdity thrown at it, than its own impudence and filthineſs. For if Chriſt's Merits be infinite, and his Raiment (which he proffereth freely) be white as ſnow, what neceſſity is there to <hi>lay out our money for that which doth not profit,</hi> and buy filthy rags which cannot cover our nakedneſs?</p>
            <p>My tenth Objection ſhall be againſt the <hi>Adoration of Images.</hi> For notwithſtanding that the <hi>changing the Glory of the Incorruptible God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Image made like to corruptible Man, and to Birds and Four-footed Beaſts, and creeping things,</hi> was the abomination of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whom <hi>(being vain in their Imaginations)</hi> God gave up to vile Affections; yet are not Papiſts aſhamed to build the Sepulchers of their Fathers, painting the Immortal Deity, in ſimilitudes of their own Invention. O Fools! Doth not God <hi>fill Heaven and Earth?</hi> Are not all Nations, before him, <hi>leſs than Nothing and Vanity? To whom then will ye liken him?</hi> Or, <hi>Who ſhall be his equal?</hi> It would be reputed a ſpiteful piece of Miſdemeanour, if not High Treaſon, in any Subject to take the Picture of a Hog, Dog, or Bear, and ſet it up in his Chamber, and call it the Picture of his King. Yet there is greater diſparity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and the beſt of Creatures, than betwixt a King and a Bear. And what an impudent deluded thing is it in them, to pray to the Images of ſuppoſed Saints, Statues, Stocks and Stones, Gods of their own making, and not acknowledge themſelves Idolaters: For (ſay they) <hi>We Worſhip not the Image or Statue, but its Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> But, O deluded Wretches! What Fool will conclude that the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they Worſhipped their Molten Calf, did believe that it was their real God, (which had ſmitten <hi>Aegypt</hi> with Plagues, and divided the Red Sea before them) but only his Repreſentative? Yet, for their Idolatry, how many thouſands fell in one day? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it leſs ſin, to pray to Angels and Saints, than to Idols of Stone, Wood and Clay; for if there be but one Omnipotent, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153613:10"/>
God, who is only able and willing, at all times, to hear and help us. How dare you ſlight him, (who inviteth us freely,) to embrace thoſe, who are neither able to hear nor help? For Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts cannot deny that they pray, <hi>Holy</hi> Michael, <hi>defend us in Battel, that we periſh not in the fearful Judgment.</hi> And to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin, O Glorious Saint, in whom I put my truſt, the Mother of Grace;</hi> The <hi>Port of Salvation, my Confidence, my Refuge, and my only hope, &amp;c.</hi> And to another, thus: <hi>Let me obtain Heaven by the Blood of St.</hi> Thomas Becket; as if the blood of a Traytor were more efficacious and propitiatory, before God, than the blood of Chriſt. Moreover, what an abominable thing is it to pray to St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> to protect Mariners, St. <hi>Luke</hi> Painters, St. <hi>Criſpin</hi> Shooe-makers, St. <hi>Gal</hi> Geeſe, and <hi>Antony</hi> Pigs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if God, whoſe Providence reacheth the Sparrows, were not the Confidence of all the ends of the Earth, and of thoſe who are afar off, upon the Seas. Moreover, it is ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to pray to that which can neither hear nor help, and ſay, O <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſs help me.</hi> And again, <hi>ange piis juſtitiam, reiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dona veniam,</hi> Increaſe Righteouſneſs in the Godly, and grant Pardon to Sinners. And to an old rag to ſay, O <hi>Sancte Sudari! Ora pro nobis,</hi> O Holy Napkin pray for us. Theſe are the Works of Deluſion, yea, the Myſtery of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> which I earneſtly deſire and requeſt all Papiſts to forſake, and pray only to God in Chriſt, the only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator and Advocate betwixt God and Man, as <hi>Jerom</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Riparius</hi> Writeth; <hi>Chriſtians, neither adore nor Worſhip Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, nor Sun, nor Moon, nor Angels, leſt they ſhould therein rather ſerve Creatures than the Creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My eleventh Objection, againſt Papiſts, ſhall be their <hi>praying in an unknown Tongue;</hi> for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Except ye utter by the tongue, words eaſie to be underſtood, how ſhall it be known what is ſpoken, for ye ſhall ſpeak unto the Air?</hi> Yea, in this ſame Chapter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. he compareth thoſe who are guilty of this foolery, to <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Mad-men;</hi> and telleth, that <hi>tongues are for a ſign to them that believe not,</hi> but <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> to them that believe. Moreover, to be ſpoke to with ſtammering lips, and Men of another tongue, was a Curſe from God upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as it is now on the obſtinate <hi>Romans</hi> this day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.11.</p>
            <p>My twelfth and laſt Objection, ſhall be againſt their <hi>Doctrine of Adultery,</hi> or their <hi>Clergies ſingle life;</hi> wherein they condemn their <hi>Sacrament of Marriage</hi> as an unholy thing, and a ſtumbling-block, in the way to Heaven. God appointed it from the beginning, Chriſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153613:11"/>
countenanc'd it, and the Apoſtle recommended it as <hi>honourable to all Men.</hi> What then are they, who give the lye both to God and Man, terming it unholy and unclean, whilſt God hath affirmed the contrary, in as direct and plain terms as any man, yea, beyond what the Wiſeſt Orator can expreſs? But (ſince this is ſo plain an abſurdity in it ſelf) I ſhall not ſpend Pen and Ink, in proving that which no rational man will deny; only ſuffer me at laſt now to treat, or rather ſurfeit your Eyes and Ears, with one abominable Story, which is this: <hi>Hudericus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Auguſta,</hi> in an Epiſtle, Writeth to Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> I. that <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great bound the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy to a ſingle Life; but on a certain time, a Woman catching ſmall fiſhes (which this ſuperſtitious Monk thought only lawful to be eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) found 6000 Heads of Infants, which had been therein drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which Monk <hi>Gregory</hi> perceiving to be the effect of the <hi>Clergies ſingle Life,</hi> with ſighing and ſorrowing, he revoked the Canon. Yea, it is reported by the foreſaid Biſhop, that the Clergy did ſo burn in Luſt, that they not only kept Company with Married Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and their own Kindred, but with Mankind, and the very Beaſts in the Field. Another Story, the Parallel whereof you may read in ſeveral Popiſh Hiſtorians, is this: <hi>Leander</hi> and <hi>Tritemius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that about the year of our Lord 1470, <hi>Alanus de Rupe,</hi> a Dominican, after he had ſeen ſeveral Viſions, contrived his Work called <hi>Roſarium,</hi> out of <hi>our Ladies Pſalter,</hi> and Preach'd it inſtead of the Goſpel; which Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> IV. confirmed, with Bulls and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences: Whereupon a certain Book was publiſhed, in the beginning whereof is Written, that the B. Virgin came into the Cell of the ſaid <hi>Alan,</hi> it being ſhut, and made him a Ring of her own Hair, and betrothed her ſelf to the Monk, kiſſing him, and giving him leave to handle her Breaſts; and finally, to be as intimate as Man and Wife. This is he from whom ſprang the Order of <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and whoſe Miracles the Popiſh Clergy ſo zealouſly defend.</p>
            <p>I thought to have ſpoken ſomething of ſeveral other Popiſh Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, eſpecially of Pennance, Pardons and Indulgences, but leſt I weary you, I ſhall only refer you to a little Pamphlet, ſold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London,</hi> Intituled, <hi>Sodom Fair,</hi> which diſcovereth the Nakedneſs and Abominations of the Romiſh Harlot to the Life, or rather Death; from which I pray God may deliver us all.</p>
            <p>I reſolved once, as I have ſaid, to have given you a taſte of all the poyſonous and counterfeit Merchandize, that is expos'd in the Market of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> and a touch of all his Hocus Tricks,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153613:11"/>
and Popiſh Pranks: But he who readeth with an Impartial Eye conſidereth with an Unprejudic'd Underſtanding, and receiveth what I have here written in an honeſt Heart, will be ready to turn his back on <hi>Babilon,</hi> and his face <hi>Zion</hi>-ward, and enquire after the good old way, which is ſet before us, in the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is my humble and hearty Advice, that all people be terrified at the Name of <hi>Popery,</hi> and that all <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> open their obſtinate Eyes and Ears, to ſee and hear the Word of Truth, and with the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſearch the Scriptures, the Writings of the Fathers; yea, and their own Legends and Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, to ſee whether what the Chriſtian Proteſtant Churches affirm, be conform to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles or not: <hi>Then if Baal be God</hi> follow him; if the Pope or his Creature the <hi>Hoſte,</hi> his imaginary Deity be God, follow him: But if there be no God but one, all ſufficient, eternal, inviſible, and incomprehenſible, follow him, according to his own Will, and the Rule which he hath in his Word preſcribed to us; but if you will neither hear, nor believe the Word of God, and Scriptures of Truth, nor the Writings of the Fathers, and of <hi>your own Hiſtorians,</hi> then if one ſhould come from the Dead, you will neither hear nor believe him: For they that ſhut both Eyes and Ears, and reſolve to be filthy, will be filthy ſtill. And none can do more, but with the Prophet <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.8. Wail over you, and cry out <hi>We would bave healed Babilon, but ſhe is not healed.</hi> But remember what the Lord ſaith by the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.11. <hi>Behold all ye that kindle a Fire, that compaſs your ſelves about with ſparks: Walk in the light of your fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kindled. This ſhall ye have of mine hand, ye ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153613:12"/>
            <head>A WORD To the People called QUAKERS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 4.16.</hi>
                  </bibl> Am I therefore become your Enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Intended to have ſpoken of your Opinions and Principles, but (conſidering that you all pretend to an Inſpiration, of the <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llble Spirit of Truth,</hi> and need no outward teachers) I ſhall only humbly adviſe you to ſquare your profeſſion, and <hi>try your Spirits,</hi> by the Scriptures of Truth; for <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets:</hi> And if you walk not after that Rule, which God hath ſet down, in his Written <hi>Word</hi> and holy <hi>Will,</hi> it is, <hi>becauſe there is no light in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, I cordially requeſt you to conſider, that all ages, ſince our Saviour's days, did repute them Hereticks, who denied the ſanctified uſe, and benefit of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> which God, in Chriſt, hath appointed, as <hi>Seals</hi> of the <hi>New Covenant;</hi> to be an Evidence before the World, that (as we really believe in our hearts before God) we are not aſhamed, before men, to own him, for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, whoſe body was broken, and whoſe blood was ſhed, for the Remiſſion of our Sins, and Salvation of our Souls. And tho you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them fooliſh and ridiculous, God by the fooliſhneſs of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153613:12"/>
yea, of Baby-ſprinkling, Bread-eating, and Wine-drinking, hath oft-times conveyed Grace, Comfort and Strength, to weary, fainting Souls. Neither can you wipe off what I affirm, by ſaying they were but <hi>beggarly Rudiments,</hi> for young beginners, to endure but for a ſhort ſeaſon. For our <hi>Saviour,</hi> in his <hi>laſt Will,</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended them to his Apoſtles, as a Chriſtian performance, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure till the end of the World. Baptiſm he did <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt: teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commanded you: and lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the World.</hi> Now (ſince <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is one among theſe <hi>all things</hi> which Chriſt hath <hi>commanded;</hi> to the peformance of which, he hath promiſed his aſſiſting preſence, to the Worlds end) it cannot be a <hi>tranſient Neceſſarium ſecundum quid,</hi> a thing that may be done or ſlighted; and that, but for a ſhort ſpace, for the Words are <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them,</hi> viz. <hi>all Nations.</hi> Now when there are no <hi>Nations,</hi> there will be no Baptiſm; but as long as there is any Nation, or one Man of a Nation, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> will never be an uſeleſs <hi>Rudiment</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inſtitution, or that which may be thrown away as a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Tradition. And, as for the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> our Saviour ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.19. <hi>This do in Remembrance of me.</hi> Now if the time be expired, wherein we ſhould not remember our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi> and the time come wherein we ſhould forget him, then may we lawfully lay by his <hi>Sacrament. Sed falſum prius ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next advice, that I would give <hi>Quakers,</hi> is negative, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of Fact; and that is, that they neither lye, cheat, nor covet: For he that ſaith that he is <hi>Religious,</hi> taught, and led by the Spirit of Truth, and doth ſuch things, his ſhow of Religion is vain; he is yet blind, and not <hi>purged</hi> from the Old Man: <hi>Love not the World</hi> (then) <hi>neither the things that are in the World. If any man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> adviſeth us to a good Religion, <hi>Chap</hi> 6.8. <hi>To do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> Which if all would ſtudy, before they fall by the ears in controverſie, for the tithes of <hi>Mint and Rue,</hi> there would be more ſincere knowledge in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, more inward Peace and outward Content, and greater practice of true piety. For the Lord ſaith, by his prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 50.23. <hi>To him that ordereth his Converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</hi> Now to this God, only Wiſe, be aſcribed all Glory, Honour and Praiſe, with Dominion, Majeſty and Might, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
